I Am Iron Man is a documentary film directed by Jon Mefford.
A documentary covering pre-production topics like suit design and construction, storyboards, animatics, and
pre-viz, sets, working in the suit, casting, rehearsals, and preparation, and the start of the shoot.
From there we look at performances, locations and production design, stunts,
hardware and practical effects, and various sequence specifics.
Finally, the program goes through post-production at Skywalker Ranch, the
titles and a few visual elements, and wrapping up the flick.
Self, played by Robert Downey Jr..
Self, played by Gwyneth Paltrow.
Self, played by Jon Favreau.
Self, played by Terrence Howard.
Self, played by Jeff Bridges.
Self, played by Stan Lee.
Iron Man is a 2008 American superhero film based on the
Marvel Comics character of the same name.
Produced by Marvel Studios and distributed by Paramount Pictures, it is
the first film in the Marvel Cinematic Universe (MCU).
Directed by Jon Favreau from a screenplay by the writing teams of Mark Fergus and Hawk
Ostby, and Art Marcum and Matt Holloway, the film stars Robert Downey Jr.
as Tony Stark / Iron Man alongside Terrence Howard, Jeff
Bridges, Gwyneth Paltrow, Leslie Bibb, and Shaun Toub.
In the film, following his escape from captivity by a terrorist group, world-famous industrialist and
master engineer Stark builds a mechanized suit of armor and becomes the superhero Iron Man.
A film featuring Iron Man was in development at Universal Pictures, 20th Century Fox, and New Line
Cinema at various times since 1990 before Marvel Studios reacquired the rights in 2005.
Marvel put the project in production as its first
self-financed film, with Paramount Pictures distributing.
Favreau signed on as director in April 2006 and faced opposition from Marvel when
trying to cast Downey in the title role; the actor was signed in September.
Filming took place from March to June 2007, primarily in California to differentiate the
film from numerous other superhero stories that are set in New York City.
During filming, the actors were free to create their own dialogue
because pre-production was focused on the story and action.
Rubber and metal versions of the armor, created by Stan Winston's company, were
mixed with computer-generated imagery to create the title character.
Iron Man premiered in Sydney on April 14, 2008, and was released in the United
States on May 2, as the first film in Phase One of the MCU.
It grossed over $585 million, becoming the eighth-highest grossing film of 2008, and received praise from critics, especially
for Downey's performance as well as Favreau's direction, the visual effects, action sequences, and writing.
The American Film Institute selected it as one of the ten best films of 2008.
It received two nominations at the 81st Academy Awards for
Best Sound Editing and Best Visual Effects.
In 2022, the Library of Congress selected the film for preservation in the United States National
Film Registry for being "culturally, historically, or aesthetically significant".
Two sequels have been released: Iron Man 2 (2010) and Iron Man 3 (2013).